Guide to the Poles in Western Pennsylvania Collection, 1910s-1990s AIS.1965.16
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Poles in the United States and Western Pennsylvania, I.
  - Culture and Heritage, 1868-1996; 5.
    This subseries is divided into three sections: Ethnic Heritage, Culture, and Musicians. A large portion of this subseries is about the Polish-American community in Pittsburgh, but there are many documents concerning the Polish-American community in Western Pennsylvania and the United States as a whole.
    The Ethnic Heritage section of this series mainly concerns the academic study of ethnicity, legislation concerning ethnicity, and the ethnic identity of the Polish-American community. Included in this section are documents about the Ethnic Heritage Studies Act (EHSA). The EHSA was introduced to Congress on January 3, 1973 and sponsored by Representative Robert A. Roe from New Jersey. The bill authorized grants to educational institutions for use in establishing and operating ethnic heritage studies projects. The bill passed in 1974. Also included are documents about the Ethnic Heritage Studies Program at the University of Pittsburgh as well as essays on the topic of Polish-American ethnic heritage from Alliance College. The majority of these documents are essays and information about specific projects. Also included are press releases from Senator Richard S. Schweiker about the EHSA. All of the documents in this section are in English.
    The Culture section of this subseries mainly concerns specific cultural traditions within the Polish-American community. Included is information about Christmas, Easter, and Lent. There are also song books and books about traditional decorations and dances. This section includes handwritten notes by Joseph Borkowski about Polish musicians. There is also a play in Polish entitiled Flower Basket. Most of these documents are books and pamphlets and there are some newspaper articles and essays. The majority of the documents in this section are in English and a few are in Polish.
    The Musicians section of this subseries contains newspaper articles, journal articles, and programs about Polish and Polish-American musicians. The majority of the concerts and events took place in Pittsburgh. Notable musicians include Ignacy Jan Paderewski (1860 - 1941), Josef Hofmann (1876 - 1957), and Henri Wieniawski (1835 - 1880). Most of the musicians included in this section were active in the late nineteenth and early twentiteth centuries. The majority of the documents in this section are in English and a few are in Polish.
    - Ethnic Heritage, 1967-1996; 1967-1980; 1.
      - 360 Years of Polish-American Heritage, speech given by BG Charles A. Symroski (Duquesne University), August 17, 1968 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
      - A Plan for the Establishment of a University Affiliated Center for the Study of American National Ethnic Traditions, by Otto can Mering (University of Pittsburgh), June 30, 1969 (Folder 2)
      - American Polonia in the 1970s, booklet and list of major events (Folder 3)
      - Application for Federal Assistance, Polish Colonial and Revolutionary War Pioneers, Joseph Borkowski, April 19, 1974 (Folder 4)
      - Bicentennial Celebration Proposal, correspondence (Pittsburgh), November 1973 – December 1974 (Folder 5)
      - Bishop Calls Polish Jokes "A Good Thing", newspaper clipping, newspaper unknown (Michigan), no date (Folder 6)
      - Catholic Conference on Ethnic and Neighborhood Affairs, information and Agenda (Pittsburgh), February 27, 1975 (Folder 7)
      - Catholics Design New Ethnic Mass, newspaper clipping, the New York Times, November 30, 1975 (Folder 8)
      - Ethnic Awareness and Self-Identity, by Rev. Leonard F. Chrobot, (Orchard Lake, MI), April 1974 (Folder 9)
      - Ethnic Heritage Studies in Danger Again, newspaper article, (Chicago, IL), March 24, 1974 (Folder 10)
      - Ethnic Heritage Studies Program, correspondence (Pittsburgh), March 1974 – July 1975 (Folder 11)
      - Ethnic Heritage Studies Program, Guidelines for Application, April 1, 1974 (Folder 12)
      - Ethnic Identity Resurgence, two newspaper articles, Pittsburgh Post Gazette (Pittsburgh), May 15, 1972 (Folder 13)
      - Ethnic Studies Program, Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, (Harrisburg, PA), 1972 (Folder 14)
      - Ethnic Village Planning Questions and Responses (Allegheny County), November 17, 1977 (Folder 15)
      - First Slavic Studies Workshop in America, series of five articles by Clarke Thomas (University of Pittsburgh), November 4, 1976 (Folder 16)
      - International Conference on Historic and Cultural Preservation, (Williamsburg, VA and Philadelphia, PA), September 10 – 15, 1972 (Folder 17)
      - Local Neighborhoods' Polish Heritage will be Explored During Programs, newspaper clipping, (Pittsburgh), October 1983 (Folder 18)
      - Memorial Day Program, Polish-American VFW Post #3257, (Wilmington, DE), May 30, 1994 (Folder 19)
      - Myth of Polish-American Anti-Semitism, editorial, Narod Polski, no date (Folder 20)
      - Orchard Lake Center for Polish Studies and Culture, brochure, (Orchard Lake, MI), no date (Folder 21)
      - People Pittsburgh, ESAA Newsletter (Pittsburgh), June – July 1975 (Folder 22)
      - Pittsburgh Committee for the Ethnic Studies Center, meeting information and memoranda (Pittsburgh), November 1970 – June 1974 (Folder 23)
      - Polish American Day programs and newspaper clipping (Erie and Pittsburgh), 1967-1971 (Folder 24)
      - Polish Hill: The White Ethnic's Complaint, journal article by Monroe W. Karmin (Pittsburgh), August 1969 (Folder 25)
      - Polish Historical Association Plan for Cultural Preservation Conference (Orchard Lake, MI), November 22 – 24, 1996 (Folder 26)
      - Polish Sprit Night at Civic Arena, flyer (Pittsburgh), January 18, 1985 (Folder 27)
      - Polish Studies Workshop, newspaper clipping, (University of Pittsburgh), January 7, 1972 (Folder 28)
      - Polish Studies Workshop, program and summary (University of Pittsburgh), January 3, 1972 (Folder 29)
      - Reflections of a Young Polish American on the Search for Identity, by Rev. Leonard F. Chrobot (Orchard Lake, MI), February 1971 (Folder 30)
      - Senator Richard S. Schweiker Press Released Relating to the Ethnic Heritage Bill (Washington, D.C.), October 1970 – n.m. 1974 (Folder 31)
      - Summarized Observations on the Demand for Ethnic Studies by Young Americans, Dr. Josef Kubik, May 5, 1971 (Folder 32)
      - The Emergency School Aid Act of 1972, memorandum (Washington D.C.), no date (Folder 33)
      - The National Coordinating Assembly on Ethnic Studies Newsletter (Washington, D.C.), April 1973 (Folder 34)
      - The National Ethnic Studies Assembly Newsletter (Detroit, MI), February - April 1974 (Folder 35)
      - The Ohio Ethnic History Project (Columbus, OH), no date (Folder 36)
      - Western Reserve Historical Society – In Search of Ethnic History, journal article from The Ohio Archivist (Cleveland, OH), 1971 (Folder 37)
      - Writer Says Ethnicity is Here to Stay, newspaper clipping, Pittsburgh Catholic, 1974 (Folder 38)
    - Culture, 1868-1995; 1951-1988; 2.
      - 300 Polish-American Scholars End a 3-Day Symposium Here, newspaper clipping, New York Times (Colombia University), March 26, 1971 (Box 1A, Folder 39)
      - American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs National Art Exhibition, booklet, (Alliance College), August 1 – 5, 1951 (Folder 40)
      - Americanism Classes and the Flag, (Pittsburgh), 1975 (Folder 41)
      - Bitter Sorrows, newspaper clipping, no date (Folder 42)
      - Carnegie Hall 75th Season Anniversary Booklet, (New York, NY), 1966-1967 (Folder 43)
      - Cepelia Polish Folk Craft and Art Center, advertisement, (New York, NY), no date (Folder 44)
      - Challenge to Use of Polish Language in Church Services Stirs Response, letters to the Editor, the Pittsburgh Catholic, (Pittsburgh), March 9, 1967 (Folder 45)
      - Christmas Catalog, "Polska" Folk Arts, (Pittsburgh), 1988 (Folder 46)
      - Christmas Customs, book in Polish, by Dr. Jan Jaworski, 1962 (Folder 47)
      - Christmas Ornaments Polish Style, book by Lawrence G. Kozlowski, 1988 (Folder 48)
      - Easter Eggs Polish Style, book by Lawrence G. Kozlowski (signed), 1977 (Folder 49)
      - Five Young Polish Davidsbundler, article, the Musical Courier, May 9, 1906 (Folder 50)
      - Flower Basket, play, no date (Folder 51)
      - Future of Polish Uncertain, newspaper clipping, The Pitt News (University of Pittsburgh), February 15, 1971 (Folder 52)
      - Handwritten notes by Joseph Borkowski, mostly about musicians and composers, 1868-1938 (Folder 53)
      - How Poland's Inspiring Dances Have Enriched Musical Literature, article, the Etude, no date (Folder 54)
      - Instructions for Dances of Poland, book by Stefan J. Zielinski, no date (Folder 55)
      - Kacik Wydawczyni, article, Pittsburczanin, November 19, 1965 (Folder 56)
      - Kujawiaki Dance Group of Alliance College, program (Pittsburgh), May 3, 1987 (Folder 57)
      - Observances and Ceremonies of Lent, book, (Orchard Lake, MI), 1972 (Folder 58)
      - Observations on the Proposal for the Museum of Immigration at Bedlow's Island, by Dr. Eugene Kusielewicz, (New York, NY), no date (Folder 59)
      - Operas and Plays, photocopies of programs (Pittsburgh), 1900-1936 (Folder 60)
      - Pittsburg Composition Played at Organ Dedication, article, (Pittsburgh), December 3, 1905 (Folder 70)
      - Polish Christmas Traditions articles, pamphlets, and essays, 1970-1983 (Folder 71)
      - Polish Dance Performances, newspaper clippings (Pittsburgh), February – December 1971 (Folder 72)
      - Polish Easter Traditions, program and newspaper clippings (Pittsburgh and Harrisburg, PA), 1972-1992 (Folder 73)
      - Polish Literary Milestones Exhibit, newspaper advertisement, (Detroit, MI), September 1, 1995 (Folder 74)
      - Polish Literary Milestones, Detroit Public Library Exhibit, (Detroit, MI), September 12 – November 10, 1995 (Folder 75)
      - Polish Music and Dances, multiple articles, the Etude, no date (Folder 76)
      - Polish National Congress, document with signatures, (Washington, D. C.), no date (Folder 77)
      - Polish Opera Sung for Polish Relief, article photocopy, Musical America, (Philadelphia, PA), March 18, 1916 (Folder 78)
      - Polish Song Books, 1918-1949 (Folder 79)
      - Polonia 75, list of delegates, (Washington, D.C.), November 7 – 9, 1975 (Folder 80)
      - Program, Summer Sessions in Poland, The Kosciuszko Foundation, (New York, NY), 1977 (Folder 81)
      - Reflections on the Cultural Condition of the Polish American Community, address by Dr. Eugene Kusielewicz (Alliance College), June 27 – 28, 1969 (Folder 82)
      - Revival Asked of Latin in Churches, letter to the Editor, newspaper unknown, no date (Folder 83)
      - Swieconka Closes Lenten Season, article, (Pittsburgh), April 20, 1973 (Folder 84)
      - The Development of Music in Poland, article, the Etude, no date (Folder 85)
      - The Music of Proud and Chivalrous Poland, article, the Etude, February 1915 (Folder 86)
      - The Orchard Lake Plan for the Cultural Progress of the Polish American Community in the United States, essay, by Very Rev. Walter J. Ziemba, June 1969 (Folder 87)
      - The Polish Museum of America, booklets and statistics, (Chicago, IL), 1972-1973 (Folder 88)
      - The Poznan Choir, brief history, American Tour book, 1963 (Folder 89)
      - Two Operas – A New and An Old, article, the Pittsburg Index, February 17, 1902 (Folder 90)
      - Wycinanki, history pamphlet from Pittsburgh Folk Festival (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 91)
    - Musicians, 1894-1972; 1907-1935; 3.
      - Argiewicz, Artur; Paderewski's Opera "Manru", articles (New York, NY), 1902-1915 (Box 1A, Folder 92)
      - Borowski, Felix, articles (Chicago, IL), July 2, 1923 (Folder 93)
      - Borowski, Karol, newspaper clipping, 1968 (Folder 94)
      - Chopin, Frederick, newspaper and journal articles, 1910-1929 (Folder 95)
      - Czaplinski, Henri, program photocopy (Toronto, Canada), October 22, 1921 (Folder 96)
      - Didur, Adamo, article, The Musical Courier, (New York, NY), c. 1907 (Folder 97)
      - Donahue, Lester, discovered by Mme. Modjeska, article, February 24, 1917 (Folder 98)
      - Friedman, Ignace, program photocopy (Pittsburgh), October 16, 1921 (Folder 99)
      - Hofmann, Josef, articles and program photocopies, (Pittsburgh; New York, NY), 1898-1936 (Folder 100)
      - Jarecki, Tadeusz, brief list of works, c. 1929 (Folder 101)
      - Kalisz, Effie, article, no date (Folder 102)
      - Kochanski, Paul, articles and program photocopies, (Pittsburgh), 1923-1934 (Folder 103)
      - Korolewicz, Jeanne, article, the Musical Courier, (Philadelphia, PA), February 1911 (Folder 104)
      - Kroll, William, article and program photocopy, (Pittsburgh), 1928 (Folder 105)
      - Landowska, Wanda, article and program photocopies, (Pittsburgh and Philadelphia, PA), 1925 (Folder 106)
      - Leginska, Ethel, article, c. 1923 (Folder 107)
      - Leschetizky, Marie Gabrielle, articles, 1911-1924 (Folder 108)
      - Leschetizky, Thomas, articles, 1915-1932 (Folder 109)
      - Liszniewska, Margeurite, article, Musical America, January 24, 1920 (Folder 110)
      - Michalski, Raymond, newspaper clipping, c. 1965 (Folder 111)
      - Mlynarski, Emil, articles, 1929-1935 (Folder 112)
      - Moszkowski, Maurice, article, the Musical Observer, August 1915 (Folder 113)
      - Muenz, Mieczyslaw, articles, 1923 (Folder 114)
      - Olszewska, Maria, article, July 22, 1928 (Folder 115)
      - Paderewska, Helena, obituary, c. 1934 (Folder 116)
      - Paderewski, Ignacy, newspaper articles, programs and handwritten notes, (Pittsburgh and New York, NY), 1895-1968 (Folder 117)
      - Penderewski, Krzysztof, newspaper clippings, 1968-1969 (Folder 118)
      - Rimmel, William M., newspaper clipping, Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, October 21, 1972 (Folder 119)
      - Rosenthal, Moriz, article (Abrams Falls, PA), January 30, 1899 (Folder 120)
      - Rozycki, Ludomir, article, August 30, 1925 (Folder 121)
      - Schulz, Leo, article, The Musical Observer, March 1907 (Folder 122)
      - Sembrich, Marcella, program photocopy, (Pittsburgh), March 3, 1918 (Folder 123)
      - Skalski, Andre, article, the Musical Courier, June 7, 1930 (Folder 124)
      - Slenczynski, Ruth,articles, (Pittsburgh), 1934 (Folder 125)
      - Slivinski, Josef, program photocopy, (Pittsburgh), February 1894 (Folder 126)
      - Stojowski, Sigismund, articles, 1915-1920 (Folder 127)
      - Stokowski, Leopold, article, Musical America, December 3, 1923 (Folder 128)
      - Symanowski, Karol, articles, 1931-1937 (Folder 129)
      - Szumowska, Antoinette, article, 1915 (Folder 130)
      - Waghalter, Ignaz, newspaper article, the New York Times, 1928 (Folder 131)
      - Walska, Ganna, newspaper articles (Chicago and New York), 1929 (Folder 132)
      - Wieniawski, Henri, articles, 1907-1915 (Folder 133)
      - Wieniawski, Isabella, letter to the editor, the New York Times (New York, NY), September 25, 1928 (Folder 134)
      - Wieniawski, Joseph, obituary, no date (Folder 135)
  - Religious History, 1935-1993; 1950-1975; 6.
    This subseries contains information about the religious history of the Polish-American community. The majority of the documents concern churches and religious organizations in the city of Pittsburgh and the surrounding area. Many of the materials about churches and religious organizations are anniversary books and short histories. Included in this subseries is a press centre packet about Pope John Paul II's second visit to Poland in 1983. There are also a significant number of materials about the celebrations of the millenium of Christianity in Poland held in Pittsburgh, Chicago, and Detroit. Poland became Christianized in 966 and the celebrations were held in 1966 and 1967. Essays by Joseph Borkowski based on research in this subseries are also included. Though the majority of this subseries is about the Roman Catholic Polish population, there is also an essay about the first Jewish settlers from Poland in the United States. Additionally, there is research and an essay on Unitarianism in Poland by Joseph Borkowski. Most of the material in this subseries is in English and few materials are in Polish.
    - 1000 Years of Christianity in Poland Anniversary Celebration (Chicago, IL), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1000 Years of Christianity in Poland Anniversary Celebration (Cleveland, OH), 1966 (Folder 2)
    - 1000 Years of Christianity in Poland Anniversary Celebration (Detroit, MI), 1966 (Folder 3)
    - 1000 Years of Christianity in Poland Anniversary Celebration (Pittsburgh), books and programs, 1961-1966 (Folder 4)
    - 1000 Years of Christianity in Poland Anniversary Celebration (Pittsburgh), correspondence, committees, and schedules, 1961-1966 (Folder 5)
    - 50th Anniversary of Saint Mary Assumption Church, program photocopy, (Pittsburgh), 1947 (Folder 6)
    - 80th Anniversary of St. Nicholas Church (Pittsburgh), newspaper clipping, Pittsburgh Catholic Newspaper, June 27, 1974 (Folder 7)
    - Anniversary books, churches (Pennsylvania), 1955-1981 (Folder 8)
    - Canonsburg Parish Revives Old Custom, newspaper article, (Canonsburg, PA), no date (Folder 9)
    - Chapel of Our Lady of Czestochowa Dedication and Consecration (Washington D.C.), 1964 (Folder 10)
    - Dedication of Saint Mary Assumption Church, program photocopy (Pittsburgh), 1955 (Folder 11)
    - Diocesan Union Holy Name Eucharistic Rally (Pittsburgh), 1950 (Folder 12)
    - Essay Contest, Polish Churches (Pittsburgh and Allegheny County), 1968 (Folder 13)
    - Essay, Lawrenceville English Lutheran Church, author unknown, no date (Folder 14)
    - Essay, Polish Churches and Organizations in the City of Pittsburgh by Carol Purell, no date (Folder 15)
    - Essay, The Pioneering of Ethnic Churches in Lawrenceville, author unknown, no date (Folder 16)
    - Father Stanislaus, short biography, no date (Folder 17)
    - Felician Sisters (Pittsburgh and Newark, NJ), 1973-1993 (Folder 18)
    - Founding of Polish Churches, by Joseph Borkowski (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 19)
    - Franciscan Fathers Anniversary book (Maryland), 1950 (Folder 20)
    - Franciscan Sisters of Blessed Kunegunda (Illinois), history, no date (Folder 21)
    - History of Bernadine Sisters and Sisters of the Holy Ghost, (Reading, PA and Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 22)
    - Holy Family Institute (Pittsburgh), 1950-1972 (Folder 23)
    - Holy Family Parish (Lawrenceville), 1968-1972 (Folder 24)
    - Holy Family Parish, history, by Joseph Borkowski, (Lawrenceville), no date (Folder 25)
    - Icon to Travel to 17 Area Parishes, newspaper article, the Pittsburgh Catholic (Pittsburgh), April 9, 1982 (Folder 26)
    - Immaculate Heart of Mary Church 75th Anniversary, booklet photocopy, (Polish Hill), 1972 (Folder 27)
    - Judaism, History (Lawrenceville), no date (Folder 28)
    - Lists of Polish Parishes and Pastors (Western PA), 1974-1975 (Folder 29)
    - Newspaper, Diocese of Pittsburgh, 1969 (Folder 30)
    - Original Slovak Parish in Pittsburgh to Celebrate 50th Anniversary June 11, newspaper clipping, The Pittsburgh Catholic, June 11, 1944 (Folder 31)
    - Pastor Information, the Pittsburgh Catholic (Pittsburgh), June 9, 1972 (Folder 32)
    - Polish Mass, article, Holy Family Church, (Pittsburgh), September 24, 1967 (Folder 33)
    - Polish Mission Welcomed at Mass Meeting, article, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 34)
    - Polish Parishes in the Pittsburgh Diocese, history, by Joseph Borkowski, (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 35)
    - Press Centre, Second Visit of Pope John Paul II to Poland, 1983 (Folder 36)
    - Religious Card, no date (Folder 37)
    - Review of History Book on Catholic Priests in the United States, Polish American Journal, September 1972 (Folder 38)
    - Rt. Rev. Msgr. R. Labujewski Memorial Dedication, 1971 (Folder 39)
    - Sacred Heart Parish Diamond Jubilee, newspaper article, (Braddock, PA), October 27, 1972 (Folder 40)
    - Saint Hedwig Church (Wilmington, DE), 1993 (Folder 41)
    - Sisters of the Holy Ghost (Pittsburgh), history, 1973 (Folder 42)
    - Sisters of the Holy Nazareth (Bellevue), 1935-1975 (Folder 43)
    - St. Hyacinth Church (Monessen, PA), no date (Folder 44)
    - St. Nicholas Church Memorial Book, photocopy (Millvale, PA), 1950 (Folder 45)
    - St. Stanislaus Church, (Ambridge, PA), 1966-1974 (Folder 46)
    - St. Stanislaus, 900th Anniversary, 1979 (Folder 47)
    - Synodal Working Commissions (Pittsburgh), 1969 (Folder 48)
    - Tri-State Inter-Diocesan Observance, 600th Anniversary of the Miraculous Appearance of Our Lady at Czestochowa, Poland (Pittsburgh), Souvenir Program, 1983 (Folder 49)
    - Unitarianism, Essay by Joseph Borkowski, no date (Folder 50)
    - Unitarianism, History, 1974 (Folder 51)
  - Other Eastern European Communities, 1942-1980; 1950-1974; 7.
    This subseries mainly contains documents about the Slovakian, Slovenian, and Croatian communities in Lawrenceville. There is an essay by Joseph Borkowski about each of these communities based in part on research from this subseries. Also included is information on a Hungarian Folk Symposium at Dusquesne Univeristy in 1980 and surveys of ethnic groups in Pennsylvania as a whole as well as Allegheny county. There is also a list of Slovenian businesses and organizations in Pittsburgh and handwritten notes from the Pittsburgh Catholic between 1942 and 1945 by Joseph Borkowski. All of the documents in this subseries are in English.
    - 25th Anniversary of American Slovene Day, booklet photocopy, (Pittsburgh), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - 50th Anniversary of the Slovenian Auditorium of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, program photocopy, 1961 (Folder 53)
    - A Symposium of Hungarian Folk Cultures (Duquesne University), April 15 and 16, 1980 (Folder 54)
    - An Ethnic Profile of Pennsylvania's Population, essay by John E. Bodnar, 1973 (Folder 55)
    - Croatian Immigrants in Pittsburgh, book chapter and newspaper clipping, photocopies, no date (Folder 56)
    - Croatian Immigration to Allegheny County, article, Zajednicar, September 12, 1956 (Folder 57)
    - Essay, Croatians of the Lawrenceville Area, by Joseph Borkowski, no date (Folder 58)
    - Essay, The Slovaks of Lawrenceville, by Joseph Borkowski, 1974 (Folder 59)
    - Essay, The Slovenes of Lawrenceville, by Joseph Borkowski, no date (Folder 60)
    - Handwritten Notes by Joseph Borkowski, mostly from The Pittsburgh Catholic, 1942-1945 (Folder 61)
    - List of Slovenian Businesses and Organizations (Pittsburgh), no date (Folder 62)
    - Slovaks in Obscurity, article, Bethlehem Bulletin, (Bethlehem, PA), March 18, 1971 (Folder 63)
    - Slovenian Americans, newspaper clipping, (Pittsburgh), January 9, 1972 (Folder 64)
    - Survey of Ethnic Groups in the Lawrenceville Area Response from St. Elizabeth's Church (Arsenal, PA), 1974 (Folder 65)
  - Polish Communities Beyond Pittsburgh, 1608-1994; 1964-1977; 8.